<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Xia&#39;s Notes</title>
  
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="http://www.xialibin.top/"/>
  <updated>2017-04-09T08:01:57.861Z</updated>
  <id>http://www.xialibin.top/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>BentleyXia</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>当然我咋i扯淡</title>
    <link href="http://www.xialibin.top/2017/04/09/post/"/>
    <id>http://www.xialibin.top/2017/04/09/post/</id>
    <published>2017-04-09T03:36:40.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-04-09T08:01:57.861Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote class="blockquote-center">当然我在扯淡 –王垠</blockquote>

<a id="more"></a>  
<p>王垠这个人挺有意思的，川大保送清华直博，进而先后在清华、cornell、IUB 退学，进而先后进入Google 、MS ，近日表示决定回国创业。上午无聊看了眼知乎，发现了王垠的博客更新，随手翻一翻，挺有意思的，他在这篇更新里这样评论自己：</p>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>在代码的优雅，简单和可靠性上，世界上还真没有人可以跟王垠抗衡。</li>
<li>微软有一些厉害的 principal engineer，他们的 B+ 树代码我看过了。实话说吧，虽然可以用，但非常繁复没法看，很难确信它是正确的。</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>对于他的技术水平和三观，可以去他的 <a href="(http://www.yinwang.org/)">博客:当然我在扯淡</a> 上去看，我没什么好讲的。倒是他的这篇 <a href="(http://www.yinwang.org/blog-cn/2014/09/17/rss)">RSS与三不主义</a> 让我觉得很有道理啊：</p>
<blockquote>
<p>本来读者是“主动”来看我的博客，我是“被动”的，是不需要负责的。然而一旦有了 RSS，每一次发布却感觉好像是我“主动”在推给他们看，是我很想让他们看一样，是要负责的。某些人取消关注别人的微博时，口气总是好像觉得自己关注一个人，是给了他很大的面子一样，所以他们用取消关注来表示他们的“惩罚”。这些人显然把自己看得太高贵了。</p>
</blockquote>
<p>为什么大家都不喜欢在 微信、QQ 上面更新状态了，甚至发了微博还觉得没有安全感，一个是把自己看得太重要了，另一个就是害怕暴露自己的内心缺点吧，感觉朋友圈的背后总是少了点真实。至于我为什么跑来这里，为了自由，为了缓解压力，所以说 “在我地盘这，就得听我的” ，老子爱说啥说啥，随意发泄自己的情绪，来不来我的私人站点是你的事，看不看是你的事，至于心情好不好，自然也就是你的事情，在这点上我同意王垠的看法，以前很多时候我都太在意别人的看法了。</p>
<p>其实我压力真的很大，就目前来看，我还是摆脱不了其他人的看法，总觉得要做点什么让人瞧得起，这不就是从小到大被灌输的思想吗？虽然我做事情一直就是特立独行，父母是左右不了的，但我也经历过失败，事实证明，不努力学习是不行的，而我读了十多年书才明白这个道理。虽说我曾经看起来很光鲜，天才、学霸、运动健将、男神，但这些称不起来更加鲜活的人生啊。所以，从这个学期开始我开始准备考研了，从 EE 转向 CS ，我为什么会有这样的决定？因为 CS 热门，薪资待遇高？并不是；因为我对计算机科学爱得深沉？也不是；因为本科专业就业前景不好？不是。因为我选择了对我本科阶段糟糕生活状态的逃避，选了一个能自己能接受的行业，一个足够证明自己的难度，以及能让这一切都变得不那么重要的新起点，这就是我想要做出改变的终极原因吧。前前前女友的那句 Loser 久久回响在我的心底，她现在 Harvard，估计早就忘了我，但我忘不下这句话，以后至少要给自己一个交待。想要逃避过去的种种不幸，那就换个起点重新开始吧…</p>
<p>说到这里，我的膝盖积水依旧没有好，因为不时的运动医生说我这一年白养了。曾经各种运动都是我排解情绪的良药，但现在这个权利也没了，希望自己克制住，为了未来，好好养伤，好好学习，希望明年的这个时候能够爬上北高峰，自己还是一条男神 。</p>
<p>真的就是在毫无营养含量的扯淡，push一下，滚去吃饭学习了</p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote-center&quot;&gt;当然我在扯淡 –王垠&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="diary" scheme="http://www.xialibin.top/categories/diary/"/>
    
    
      <category term="life" scheme="http://www.xialibin.top/tags/life/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>写在前面的话</title>
    <link href="http://www.xialibin.top/2017/04/08/hello-world/"/>
    <id>http://www.xialibin.top/2017/04/08/hello-world/</id>
    <published>2017-04-08T02:03:14.629Z</published>
    <updated>2017-04-09T08:05:45.303Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="Preface"><a href="#Preface" class="headerlink" title="Preface"></a>Preface</h3><blockquote>
<center><i class="icon-book">  Sadly, Fate had made me good, not great.  –Phil Knight</i></center>

</blockquote>
<a id="more"></a>
<p>上面这段话来自最近在看一本耐克创始人Phill Knight的自传 <a href="https://www.gatesnotes.com/Books/Shoe-Dog" target="_blank" rel="external"><strong><em>Shoe Dog</em></strong></a>，是在比尔盖茨的 <a href="https://www.gatesnotes.com" target="_blank" rel="external"><strong><em>GatesNotes</em></strong></a> 书单中淘得。</p>
<h3 id="Blog"><a href="#Blog" class="headerlink" title="Blog"></a>Blog</h3><ul>
<li>我为什么要写博客?</li>
</ul>
<p>上面提到 <em>BillGates</em> 的书单，是他在个人Blog上的推荐。 盖茨在退休之后开通了各种社交方式，Blog的更新频率也非常高，主要是 Books 和 Energy 。</p>
<p><a href="https://www.gatesnotes.com" target="_blank" rel="external"><strong><em>GatesNotes</em></strong></a> 重新燃起了我对Blog的兴趣，并且最近在学习《计算机网络》应用层部分，加上两年前已经搭建过独立博客 <em><a href="http://xialibin.cn" target="_blank" rel="external">http://xialibin.cn</a> </em>，就用了半个上午的时间重新用 Hexo 做好了这个站点，强烈推荐 Hexo以及选用的 <a href="http://theme-next.iissnan.com/getting-started.html" target="_blank" rel="external">Next</a> 主题，功能完整文档很详细。WordPress成本比较高，Jekyll不适合Windows，Pelican主题少，之前都亲自尝试过。 <strong><em>Flag</em></strong> :以后闲着自己再仿照 Gates 那样自己做一个。</p>
<p>最近一年比较忙碌，会尽力完成从 HIT-EE 到 ZJU-CS 的跳跃，以弥补自己高考的遗憾吧。但会保持对 <strong>读书总结</strong> 的更新，读原版书时尽量用英文去书写，同样向 <em>BillGates</em> 同学看齐，下面附上其 <strong><em>Shoe Dog</em></strong> 的读后感:</p>
<hr>
<p><center><a href="https://www.gatesnotes.com/Books/Shoe-Dog" target="_blank" rel="external"><strong>An Honest Tale of What It Takes to Succeed in Business</strong></a></center></p>
<p>Many books I’ve read about entrepreneurs follow a common, and I believe misleading, storyline. It goes like this: A sharp entrepreneur gets a world-changing idea, develops a clear business strategy, recruits a crack team of partners, and together they rocket to fame and riches. Reading these accounts, I’m always struck by how they make their achievements appear to be the inevitable result of some great prescience or unusual skill. It’s no wonder publishers churn out “how-to” titles packed with tidy checklists, 5-step programs, and other simplistic recipes for entrepreneurial success.<br>Shoe Dog, Phil Knight’s memoir about creating Nike, is a refreshingly honest reminder of what the path to business success really looks like. It’s a messy, perilous, and chaotic journey riddled with mistakes, endless struggles, and sacrifice. In fact, the only thing that seems inevitable in page after page of Knight’s story is that his company will end in failure.<br>Failure, of course, is about the last thing people would associate with Nike today. The company’s sales top \$30 billion and Nike’s swoosh is one of the most universally recognized logos across the globe. Walk down almost any street in the world and you’ll likely find someone wearing a pair of Nikes. But Knight brings readers back more than 50 years to the incredibly humble and fragile beginnings of the company when he started selling imported Japanese athletic footwear out of the back of his Plymouth Valiant.<br>I’ve met Knight a few times over the years. He’s super nice, but also very quiet. Like many other people who’ve met him, I found him difficult to get to know. As famous as his company has become, Knight was a mystery among Fortune 500 executives.<br>In the pages of Shoe Dog, however, Knight opens up in a way few CEOs are willing to do. He’s incredibly tough on himself and his failings. He doesn’t fit the mold of the bold, dashing entrepreneur. He’s shy, introverted, and often insecure. He’s given to nervous ticks—snapping rubber bands on his wrist and hugging himself when stressed in business negotiations. It took him weeks to tell Penny, the woman who would become his wife, that he liked her. And yet, in spite of or perhaps because of his unusual character traits, he was able to realize the “Crazy Idea,” as he calls it, to do something different with his life and create his own shoe company.<br>Knight’s interest in shoes started at the University of Oregon, where he ran track for legendary running coach Bill Bowerman. He then went to Stanford for his MBA, where he wrote a paper about the potential market for importing Japanese athletic shoes to the U.S. At the time, Japanese cameras were making a dent in the German-dominated camera market. Why not do the same with Japanese running shoes which he thought could compete against leading German athletic shoe makers Adidas and Puma?<br>So far, this storyline may feel familiar. It’s the myth of the young entrepreneur with a world-changing idea who is headed down a straight path to success. But the rest of Knight’s journey rips that myth to shreds.<br>Much of the suspense in the book is built by the precarious nature of Knight’s finances. He started his shoe import business, known then as Blue Ribbon Sports, with \$50 from his father. It was the beginning of many years of living in debt. Year after year, he goes on his knees to his bankers to beg for more credit so he could import more Japanese shoes. He rarely had any savings in the bank because he would plow all of his profits back into the company to order more shoes from Japan. Even as sales of his shoes took off, his business was constantly on life support. Meanwhile, he had a rocky relationship with his Japanese shoe supplier, whose executives were constantly eyeing other potential U.S. partners, despite Knight’s success selling and helping to improve the designs of their shoes. Eventually, Knight broke away and started Nike, beginning another round of uncertainty.<br>Knight is amazingly honest about the accidental nature of his company’s success. Consider the famous Nike swoosh. He paid an art student $35 to design it, but he didn’t recognize what a special logo it would become. “It’ll have to do,” he said at the time. The decision to call the company Nike was also not Knight’s top choice. He wanted to name it Dimension Six, but his employees pushed him to choose Nike. At the time, Knight agreed but he was not convinced. “Maybe it will grow on us,” he said.<br>When I was starting Microsoft I was fortunate enough that I was entering a business that didn’t have such tight margins. I didn’t struggle with banks to get financing as Knight did. I also didn’t need to struggle with the large factories, which I wish Knight spent more time explaining. After reading close to 400 pages about the shoe business, I was disappointed that I didn’t learn more about what it takes to manufacture an athletic shoe: what are all the parts of the shoe? which ones are difficult to manufacture and why?<br>What I identified most with from his story were the odd mix of employees Knight pulled together to help him start his company. Among them, a former track star paralyzed after a boating accident, an overweight accountant, and a salesman who obsessively wrote letters to Knight (to which Knight never responded). They were not the people you would expect to represent a sportswear company. It reminded me of my very early days at Microsoft. Like Knight, we pulled together a group of people with weird sets of skills. They were problem solvers and people who shared a common passion to make the company a success. We all worked hard, but it was also lots and lots of fun.<br>Readers looking for a lesson from Knight’s book may leave this book disappointed. I don’t think Knight sets out to teach the reader anything. There are no tips or checklists. Instead, Knight accomplishes something better. He tells his story as honestly as he can. It’s an amazing tale. It’s real. And you’ll understand in the final pages why, despite all of the hardships he experienced along the way, Knight says, “God, how I wish I could relive the whole thing.”</p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;h3 id=&quot;Preface&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Preface&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Preface&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Preface&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;icon-book&quot;&gt;  Sadly, Fate had made me good, not great.  –Phil Knight&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Dairy" scheme="http://www.xialibin.top/categories/Dairy/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Life" scheme="http://www.xialibin.top/tags/Life/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
